<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of some passages which passed at Madrid in the year 1623. by Prince Charles, being then in Spain prosecuting the match with the Lady Infanta. As also, severall observations of eleven ominous presages, some of them hapning in the same hear whil'st the said Prince was in Spain, the rest of them hapned from that time untill his death. With a discovery of some of the wayes which the then Popish Bishops used to bring Poperie into this nation. / By a lover of the Gospel of Jesus Christ, and the wellfare of this nation.</title>
            <author>Lover of the gospel of Jesus Christ, and the wellfare of this nation.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95181</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2918</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E842_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207227</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866293</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866293</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118561</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95181)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118561)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 128:E842[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of some passages which passed at Madrid in the year 1623. by Prince Charles, being then in Spain prosecuting the match with the Lady Infanta. As also, severall observations of eleven ominous presages, some of them hapning in the same hear whil'st the said Prince was in Spain, the rest of them hapned from that time untill his death. With a discovery of some of the wayes which the then Popish Bishops used to bring Poperie into this nation. / By a lover of the Gospel of Jesus Christ, and the wellfare of this nation.</title>
                  <author>Lover of the gospel of Jesus Christ, and the wellfare of this nation.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 14".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118561:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRUE RELATION OF Some paſſages which paſſed at
<hi>Madrid</hi> in the year 1623. by Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> being then in
<hi>Spain</hi> proſecuting the match with the Lady <hi>Infanta. AS
ALSO,</hi> Severall Obſervations of eleven <hi>Ominous Preſages,</hi>
ſome of them hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the ſame year whil'ſt the ſaid Prince was in
<hi>Spain,</hi> the reſt of them hapned from that time untill his death. With
a diſcovery of ſome of the wayes which the then Popiſh Biſhops uſed
to bring Poperie into this Nation.</p>
            <p>By a lover of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, and the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare
of this Nation.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118561:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118561:2"/>
            <head>To the Impartial Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Had no intent ever to have put in print theſe Ominous
Preſages, for they have been of an ancient ſtanding in my head; (the moſt
part of them) old things being fit for nothing but to be forgotten, or at
leaſt laid aſide. But a friend of mine knowing that I had obſerved them
long agoe (ſome of them being of 30. years ſtanding or more) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired me
to give him a ſhort brief of them, which I did, but when I had collected my
memory, and ſaw the troubles that do dayly increaſe by ſome who delight
to fiſh in troubled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and conſidering that there are many good
people that are not yet ſetled in their hearts concerning theſe mutable
times, but do ſtill continue oppoſite to the Government as now it is, and
do not once think of, or it may be never heard of any of thoſe ſad
Preſages which the Lard ſent to give warning to thoſe that would take
warning or notice of them and lay them to their hearts. I did alſo then
conſider with my ſelf, that if they were publiſhed to the view of all the
Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they may give good ſatisfaction to ſome, and might draw them
from their ſelf-opinions, which of a long time they have had of theſe
moſt turbulent times, ſo that if they will but look up to God, they ſhall
plainly ſee, that the hand of God is in all the actions that hath paſſed
untill this day; and that no one tittle of the work that the Lord hath
appointed to be done, but it ſhall be fully effected, though men ſtrive
never ſo much againſt it. Therefore I deſire thee to conſider well of
what thou ſhalt find written in theſe few lines, (for they are truth) and
were acted by thoſe which ſought to bring in Popery to this Nation, in
thoſe days when <pb facs="tcp:118561:3"/>they had the reines in their own hands. And
certainly theſe Predictions are true, and were purpoſely ſent by God to
ſome (though not to all) that they might take notice of them. I having long
agoe ſpoke with ſome that did take notice of them as well as my ſelf (and
did look upon them as from the hand of God). And I do wiſh in my heart that
all thoſe into whoſe hands they ſhall come, to read them carefully and
im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print them in their hearts, and be well adviſed how they do practiſe or
contrive any thing tending to the ſhedding of any more innocent bloud in this
Nation; for certainly they will be found out, and themſelves will have as
great a ſhare in the deſtruction which they do practice as any of thoſe
ſhall have which they ſhall practiſe againſt, either in their lives,
Limbs, Estates, Wives, Children, and all that is deer unto them; nay which is
the greateſt of all, their ſouls will have the greateſt loſſe when
they ſhall loſe heaven, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the great mercy of God. I will conclude
with the words of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, O that men would fear the Lord and
praiſe his holy name, for his mercie endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for ever!</hi> For certainly
he will (as heretofore he hath done) overthrow the horſe and his rider if
they do perſiſt in their exorbitant wayes. And I will now ſay with
<hi>Paul,</hi> as in an other caſe, <hi>My hearts deſire to God is, that
men would ſerve the Lord with fear and trembling, and fit ſtill and ſee
the Lords work done in his onwn good time.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118561:3"/>
            <head>A true Relation of ſome paſſages which paſſed at
<hi>Madrid</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> in the year 1623. by Prince
<hi>Charles,</hi> being then proſecuting the Match with the Lady
<hi>Infanta.</hi> As alſo ſome Obſervations of ſeveral <hi>Ominus
Preſages,</hi> ſome of them hapning the ſame year, 1623. the reſt of
them hapning from that time until his death.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Do deſire thee to conſider with thy ſelf if thou haſt
hard of, or ſeen any of theſe obſervations following; if yea, then
whether thou didſt make that uſe of them, as was expected from Gods hands
thou ſhouldſt have done; for certainly they were not done in a corner, but
were ſent from God as forerunners of his wrath againſt the late King, and
all thoſe Popiſhly inclined Prelats, and other his abetters, that did
aſſiſt him in thoſe Practiſes and Councels, for the bringing in of
Popery into this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as it did plainly appear by the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>encing of ſo many Godly and Orthodox
Miniſters, as then were put from their preaching and livings ſince his
coming from <hi>Spain,</hi> at which time many young Divines at receiving their
O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rders for preaching, were forbidden to read certain mens works, as M.
<hi>Perkins</hi> his works, <hi>Clarks</hi> Sermons and others, and were
likewiſe limited what ſubject, they ſhould preach on, as the Lords
Prayer, the Belief, the Ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the like, and the better to
bring their practiſes to paſſe, they did cauſe all. Orthodox books that
were out of print, and to be reprinted, (although the Authors of them were dead
many years before) to be brought to the Biſhops Chaplains to be reviewed by
them, who were half, <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118561:4"/>if not altogether Popiſh, or at
leaſt Arminians, and they to expunge, or put in any Popiſh tenet, which
they thought fit to put in, although thoſe men which wrote thoſe books were
men of as ſound judgment as any of thoſe that did corrupt or abuſe their
works, and it is very likely that if the Biſhops themſeves were ſo much
given to Popery they would entertain none to be their Chaplains but ſuch as
ſhould be as themſelves were, and by that means many good Miniſters works
were corrupted, and themſelves counted Popiſh by all that ſhould read
their new reviſed works, which the Authors were no wayes guilty of. But you
will ſay that many of the Biſhops were free from Popery. It is very true,
ſome of them were ſo, but thoſe that were neareſt to the King in his
Councels were not, as <hi>Neal, Wren, Laud,</hi> and others were not; but mark
I pray you, 30. years before the Angels of <hi>England</hi> did begin to fall,
(which were the Biſhops, as Mr. <hi>Brightman</hi> a famous Divine did call
them; and one whom the then Biſhops perſecuted even to the forſaking of
his Native Countrey) he the ſaid <hi>Brightman</hi> did propheſie the
downfall of them to begin in the year 1639. which fell out very neer the time,
for in the year 1640. or very neer it, they were expelled the Parliament for
their miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menors their, for many of them appeared then to be Popiſh.</p>
            <p>And after the wars began, Biſhop <hi>Wrens</hi> houſe being
ſearched, there was found in it a new ſet of Maſſing plate, it was as
neat a ſet of plate as the Pope hath any in his Chappel. And Doctor
<hi>Peerce</hi> the then Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells</hi> (as it
was confidently ſpoken of, and likewiſe written, did ſend word to the
then Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury (Laud)</hi> and in his Letter to him, did
thanke God that he had not left a Lectur in all his Dioceſſe, (a thing
ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fit to thanke God for) But I pray take notice that all <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118561:4"/>theſe things were acted after the King came from <hi>Spain</hi> (by
the Biſhops), for the late King being in the year 1623. but Prince, was
ſent into <hi>Spain</hi> by King <hi>James,</hi> accompanied with
<hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and Sit <hi>Francis
Cotington,</hi> where after ſome treaty with the King of Spain concerning the
<hi>Infanta,</hi> (whom he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſhould have been his wife) the Divines
of <hi>Spain</hi> oppoſing the match, did put many rubs in the way, but the
chiefeſt of them was the unlawfulneſſe of matching the daughter of
<hi>Spain</hi> with an Heretick, and one that they could have no aſſurance
of, that ſhe ſhould have the free exerciſe of her religion, for her
ſelf and her retinew with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good caution given for the ſame, and no other
caution would be excepted on but the two Port Towns of <hi>Plimouth</hi> and
<hi>Dartmouth,</hi> neither did they conceive it fit to have any further treary
on the premiſes, untill ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation thereof were firſt had and obtained
from the Popes Holineſſe.</p>
            <p>And to that end the Prince writes his Lemer to his Holineſſe,
wherein he gives him the ſtyle of moſt Holy Father, and after Complements
uſed ſutable to the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of his Holineſſe, he makes known unto him
the cauſe of his ſo ſuddain coming <hi>Spain,</hi> (which as he ſaid)
was to gain the Lady <hi>Infanta</hi> to be his wife, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all related to
his Holineſſe what a dangerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence it would be to the
Catholiques of <hi>England,</hi> if the Divines of <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould make
any further ſcruple in oppoſing the match; and he did alſo profeſſe
upon the faith of a Chriſtian Prince, that he would hazard his life and all
his Kingdomes, for the propagating of the <hi>Roman-Catholick</hi> Religion,
with other circumſtances of the like nature.</p>
            <p>His Holineſſe anſwered his Highneſſe Letter with the
like Complemers, laying before him the Valour of his <pb n="4" facs="tcp:118561:5"/>noble
Anceſtors, who hazzarded their lives and all their fortunes, and all that was
deer unto them in defending the Catholick ſaith, and did not only merit unto
themſelves eternall glory and happineſſe in heaven, but gained unto
themſelves alſo, and to their poſterity, everlaſting ſame and renow
here upon earth, and then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing him) as his Anceſtors had done) to go
forward in promoting the Catholick faith and ſo with is holineſſe his
benedict on he bequeathed his highneſſe, to the protect on of the
Almighty.</p>
            <p>Yet the Divines were not ſatisfyed with his Highneſſe ſo
large promiſes to his Holineſſe, but ſtill oppoſed the match with
might and main, ſo that the Prince was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to ſend another
writing to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> of one whole ſheet of paper fully
written and ſent it by the hands of the <hi>Duke de Olavarce,</hi> intimating
what a diſhonour it would be both to his perſon and reputation, if he
ſhould not obtain the prize which he ſo much aimed at, and which he did
eſteem above all the treaſures in the whole world, and that it would be a
great hindrance to the Catholicks of <hi>England</hi> from attaining that which
now they might obtain, if he might not have her which his ſoul ſo much
deſired; but he hoped that thoſe ſo celebrious Divines would not put him
to give ſuch caution as was deſired, and as they propounded, and could not
be by him with honor granted, eſpecially in regard his Father had granted the
Catholicks of <hi>England</hi> the free exerciſe of their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeven
years before his coming into <hi>Spain,</hi> and with all exciting them to
conſider that neither his Father nor himſelf had broken their words in the
leaſt title of any the capitulations that had paſt between them, ad the
Divines in not taking the word nor Oath of his Father nor of himſelf, for
performance of what had been capitulated, would be a means to cauſe his 
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118561:5"/>Fathers vaſſals every day to raiſe new ſcruples and
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, ſo that the Catholicks of <hi>England</hi> ſhould not
injoy that freedome of the exerciſe of their Religion which now they have,
and that if he might injoy her whom his ſoul ſo much deſired, it would be
a means that none of his Fathers vaſſals ſhould dare to ſtir.</p>
            <p>And he doth alſo promiſe upon the faith of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
Prince, that nothing in the world ſhould make him break his word in the
leaſt jot or tittle of any that ſhould be capittulated on, but would
hazzard his life and all his Kingdomes, and all that was deer unto him, for the
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of the Roman Catholick Religion, for he would not be joyned to one
in the affinity of marriage, whoſe Religion he ſhould hate, which promiſe
he did faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully keep, to the ruin of himſelf, and all his
Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>But the firſt foundation of his ruin, and all their Poſterity,
was laid by his Father King <hi>James;</hi> for in the matter of Sir <hi>Thomas
Overbury</hi> his death, he did ſend for the Judges and gave them a ſtrict
charge to examine the matter throughly concerning the death of Sir <hi>Tho.
Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> and did imprecate Gods curſe upon them if they did not
diſcover it to the full; and did upon his knees call for a curſe from God,
and deſired that God would never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper him nor any of his Poſterity,
if he did ſpare any guilty perſon that had a hand in that poiſonous
murther: and the Judges having proſecuted the buſineſſe ſo far, that
they found <hi>Sommerſet</hi> and his Lady to be the chief actors in this
murther, for they found that <hi>Sommerſet</hi> did write a friendly Letter
to Sir <hi>Tho. Overbury,</hi> that he would uſe all the wayes and means to
get his inlargement that poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly he could, and in that Letter he ſent
him a paper of Powder for him to take, as being the beſt thing that
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118561:6"/>took in his ſickneſſe, (Sir <hi>Thomas</hi>
being then ſick of Poyſon ſent him before) but this powder which was
ſent in this Letter was a poyſon of a lingring nature, whereof (with ſome
other poyſon which Mris. <hi>Turner</hi> had ſent him of the like nature)
he died, and after it was ſound out, there was juſtice done upon many of
the actors, where of <hi>Weſton</hi> was the firſt, then Sir <hi>Jarvis
Elway,</hi> the then Lieutenant of the Tower, was the next that ſuffered, and
after him, Mris. <hi>Turner</hi> was alſo hanged, beſides others; and when
it was punctually proved that <hi>Summer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet</hi> and his Lady were ſound
to be the chief actors of this murther, and that he himſelf had ſent the
poyſon aforeſaid, the King contrary to the curſe which he had formerly
called from heaven upon himſelf and all his poſterity, did pandon both him
and her, after the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> had paſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death upon
them, and the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> was ever after in diſgrace with the King,
for paſſing this ſentence againſt them, and for ſome other ſmall
marter which he croſſed the Kings humour in; and ſo this noble Gentleman
was poy ſoned, for no other cauſe but for oppoſing <hi>Summerſet</hi>
in the marriage of <hi>Eſſex</hi> his wife. But the Lord did ſhew a great
example upon them both, but eſpecially upon her, for ſhe died a more
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>thſome death then any woman ever
died, but for civilities ſake I will forbear the particulars thereof.</p>
            <p>But let us now leave this, and ſpeak no more of this curſe,
but let us look up to heaven upon him that ſees all the actions that are done
on earth, and that is the contriver of all marriages on earth both great and
ſmall, and you ſmall ſee how he doth fruſtrate the deſignes of all
thoſe that have plotted the downfall of the Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt, by
bringing them to utter confuſion in all their enter priſes, and I pray
obſerve with me, how in the very interim of this <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118561:6"/>treaty the
Lord did look down from heaven upon them, and did ſend his thunders as
meſſengers of his wrath to give them warning, that he would meet with them
and confound all their deviſes.</p>
            <p>And in the firſt place be pleaſed to take notice that on
Thurſday the 30. of <hi>June,</hi> 1623. whil'ſt the Prince was in
<hi>Spain,</hi> it being but two dayes after the Letter was written to the Pope
(for it was written the 28. day of <hi>June</hi>)</p>
            <p n="1">I. The Lord was pleaſed to ſend one great clap of
Thunder, which ſtroke away the flag and flag-ſtaffe from the
main-top-maſt-head of a Ship then riding at <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll</hi> and bound for <hi>Spain</hi> with proviſion of
freſh victuals to fetch the Prince home: as live Muttons, Capons, and other
fowls fit ſot ſuch a voyage, <hi>Spain</hi> being barren of ſuch
proviſions (ſo that they could not be furniſhed there) It was as fair a
day as any hath been ſeen; it alſo ſplit the main-top-maſt, as own
would have ſplit an Oſier twig, it threw one part on one ſide of the
Ship, and the other part on the other ſide of the Ship, it raiſed the
main-maſt down to the deck, but did no other hurt to the Ship; it killed two
men and one woman at <hi>Croydon</hi> in the Biſhop of <hi>Canterburies</hi>
Dioceſſe, in a field where they were making hay. But you may object, this
was but an accident, for thunders have done many ſuch things, the bodies
being ſoorched, and their clothes not ſo much as once to ſmell of the
fire. it is very true, ſuch things have hapned many times and in many places,
but look a little further and you ſhall ſee ſuch other prodigious things
that you will not ſay they were accidentall.</p>
            <p>And now I beſeech you conſider with me whether theſe follow
Preſages be accidentall or no.</p>
            <p n="2">II. And ſee what happened on the very next Thurſday
being the 7. of our <hi>July,</hi> the Letter to the Pope being 
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118561:7"/>written the 8. of their <hi>July</hi> at <hi>Madrid</hi> in
<hi>Spain,</hi> it pleaſed, the Lord to ſend many great: claps of Thunder,
with aboundance of rain, and withall ſo great a pillar of fire from heaven
out of the South (which is the due courſe from <hi>Spain</hi>) that it
reached from the heavens to the earth, not as a flaſh of lightnings gone in
the very ſight, but a very firme pillar of fire, which I believe did amaſe
any that did behold it. It was my hap to be in the Parke neer Southwark, when
it fell right before me, and ſo deterred me, that I prayed that the Lord was
not angry with this Nation, for ſeeking to match with one whoſe Religion
was not agreeable to the Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt, but one of thoſe
claps of Thunder did ſtrike away the Crown and Vane from the top of the
Gatehouſe of St. <hi>James</hi> whereon the clock ſtood; it melted a piece
of the bell (which houſe was then the Princes houſe at that time) and he
conſtantly kept his Court there, it alſo ſtruck down a Gardner and his
wife in a Garden neer the <hi>Neathouſe</hi> neer <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi>
&amp; brak through ſeveral houſe in the bowling-alley neer
<hi>Weſtminſter</hi> aforeſaid, the man before mentioned was dead, but
the woman revived and was well again, the body of the man was ſcorched, but
his clothes had no hurt. It ſplit wainſcots, chaires, tables and ſtools
in the houſes aforeſaid. It killed alſo another man at <hi>Croydon</hi>
the ſame time. Surely theſe things cannot be accidentall, when both theſe
thunders did aime, both at the head and Crown as we may ſee it did, for the
flag is as the hat on the Kings head, for all Ships when they meet with any the
King or States ſhips at Sea, they ſtrike their topſails or the flag in
obedience or homage to the Admirall; there is no man that not is wilfully blind
but he may ſee that theſe two dayes Thunders were not accidentall, but from
the hand of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:118561:7"/>There is one thing more which a Heathen or an
Infidell will not ſay was accidentall, and that is this:</p>
            <p n="3">III. Old <hi>Thomas</hi> Earl of <hi>Arundell</hi> a great
lover of Statues, had ſent for the Kings Statue in marble out of
<hi>Italy;</hi> it being come it was landed at a little garden houſe in
<hi>Greenwitch</hi> which the Earl then had there; his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with others
coming to view the Statue, did very much commend the workmanſhip of it, but
while they were diſcourſing of it, their fell three drops of bloud on the
face of it, no man knowing how it ſhould come there; the Earl ſeeing the
bloud was very much moved at it, they uſed all the means they could uſe to
get away the bloud, but could not; this queſtionleſſe was not done by
accident, but as the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Sorcerers ſaid to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in
the plague of the lice, This is the finger of God.</p>
            <p>Yet one thing more there is remaining which I hope will give you
full ſatisfaction that theſe Preſages were ſent by God.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. For in the ſame year 1623. while the Prince was in
<hi>Spain</hi> (for then he was but Prince) promiſing to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Roman
Catholick Religion, both to the Pope and likewiſe to the King of
<hi>Spain,</hi> there was a <hi>Buckinghamſhire</hi> man, a Taylor by trade,
and as he ſaid dwelt in <hi>Ailſbury,</hi> he was neer upon 40. years of
age, and a very ſober man, he could not contain himſelf at his work in his
houſe, but muſt of force in the ſame year while the Prince was in
<hi>Spain;</hi> making thoſe promiſes to propagate the Romiſh Religion in
<hi>England</hi> aforeſaid, he did in all or moſt part of all the eminent
ſtreets in <hi>London,</hi> in that very year curſe the Romiſh Religion;
pronouncing wee to <hi>Rome,</hi> woe to the Pope, woe to all Papiſts; and
God confound the Pope and all Papiſts, and all that did adhere to Popery, by
what name or title ſo ever they were called, <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118561:8"/>whether
Dukes, Marqueſſes, Earls, Lords, Viſcounts, or of what degree ſoever;
he did conſtantly three or four dayes in the week all or moſt part of the
time the Prince was in Spain, come to <hi>Whitehall-gate,</hi> King
<hi>James</hi> being then at <hi>Whitehall</hi> for the moſt part, he did
there make a prayer of three quarters of an houre long, it was as effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all a
prayer as any Divine in <hi>England</hi> could make, in that prayer he prayed
that the Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt might ſtill continue and flouriſh in
this Nation, and after praying for the Goſpell, he again cried theſe woes
as formerly, and when he had made his prayer at <hi>Whitehall-gate,</hi> with
his hat under his arme all the time of his praying and journey (for ſo he
called it his journey, as you ſhall ſee by and by) he then betook himſelf
to march through the City, praying this prayer, and crying theſe woes and
curſings againſt Popery as aforeſaid. He began his journey at
<hi>Whitehall-gate,</hi> and marched as far as there was any houſe in
<hi>White-chappell, Eaſt-ſmithfield, Shoreditch, Iſlington,</hi> St.
<hi>Giles in the fields,</hi> the <hi>Barrough</hi> of <hi>Southwark,</hi> and
many other walkes, and in this manner he paſt through all or the moſt part
of all the ſtreets in <hi>London,</hi> and although he made the moſt part
of his prayers at <hi>Whitehall-gate</hi> King <hi>James</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then
there, yet no man reproved him for it, or asked why he did ſo, til one day
Sir <hi>Harry Spiller</hi> ſaw him crying theſe woes at the upper end of
<hi>Holborn,</hi> did ſend him to the new Bridewell neer
<hi>Clarken-well,</hi> where he remained three weeks (and then being charged as
<hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were by the Jewiſh Rabbins that he ſhould
teach no more in that name, he was let go) but he regarding not their threats
did cry theſe woes a long time after, at length he went to his houſe in
<hi>Buccingamſhire,</hi> thinking to cry theſe woes no more, but went to
fall to work at his trade, yet when he was at his work he had not the power to
finiſh it, but threw it aſide and came up to <hi>London</hi> the ſecond
time <pb n="11" facs="tcp:118561:8"/>to crie theſe woes which he did a long time
after.</p>
            <p>I did once meet him neer <hi>Biſhopſgate-ſtreet</hi> as he
was coming back from crying theſe woes, where a man of his acquaintance met
him, and asked him if he would drink a cup of beer, he ſaid he would, for
ſaid he, I have done my journey, therefore it is evident he was ſent of God
to cry theſe woes againſt the Papiſts, as the Lord ſent that man to
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi> many years before it was deſtroyed, and at laſt cryed,
Woe, woe to himſelf, and immediately was ſtruck dead by a clap of thunder.
It is much about 32. years ſince this man did cry theſe woes in
<hi>London;</hi> and who knowes but the Lord may very ſpeeddy purge this
Nation of all thoſe blaſphemous opinions which do now ſwarme in it, and
of all thoſe that do ſeek to uphold Popery or any other falſe opinions,
which this Nation is now overrun with; and I beſeech you to conſider that
this mans crying theſe woes juſt in the interim when the Prince was in
<hi>Spain</hi> acting againſt the Goſpell, it is neceſſary that we
ſhould take notice of it, and of other things of the like nature, and to the
ſame purpoſe; for afoer be was King and had mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the Queen out of
<hi>France,</hi> he did entertain <hi>Signier Con</hi> the Popes Nuncio, and
one <hi>Price</hi> Superior of the Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctine Monks, a very great Polititian
and Stateſman he was, wch two men were ſo great with <hi>Laud</hi> then
Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburyh,</hi> that they had free acceſſe to him and
<hi>Windebanck</hi> at all times; and they were ſo great with <hi>Laud</hi>
(he being a Jeſuiticall Monke) that he gave out that he ſhould have the
Cure of the Church in <hi>Cowen Garden.</hi> This <hi>Signier Con</hi> and this
<hi>Price</hi> had ſo much power with <hi>Laud</hi> and <hi>Windebanck,</hi>
that they did brave the purſevants which had Commiſſions for the
apprehending of Prieſts and Jeſuns, and did threatten them to cauſe their
Commiſſions to be taken from them; and <hi>Windebanck</hi> himſelf did
revile the <pb n="12" facs="tcp:118561:9"/>Purſevants, calling them Knaves, and threatning
them, that if they did ever meddle with any more Prieſts and Jeſuites, he
would make him ſmart for it. I my ſelf ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſeiſed a great number of
Popiſh books in Engliſh, Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> would ſend for them to
the Regiſters Office, for the high Commiſſion Court, and the ſame night
would deliver them to the owners of them to be diſperſt through the Nation,
ſo that it is evident that if the King were not Popiſhly inclined, yet the
chief Biſhops, and the chief officers about him, were abſolutely Popiſh.
I could name many more that were in great places about the King that were
Papiſts, and known to be ſo, by many that grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſee it at that
time. But let me ſpeak a little more of this man, in all the time that he was
crying theſe woes, he was never ſeen to beg or receive any thing by way of
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of any man, yet he wanted nothing that ever I could heare of, he
alwayes wore one ſute of cloth whole and ſound, and there is no queſtion
but the Lord did keep him while he was doing his work. But if there be any that
do diſtruſt the truth hereof, there be many thouſands this day living in
<hi>London,</hi> that did both hear him, and ſee him as well as my ſelf,
while he was doing his work.</p>
            <p n="5">V. After this one of the Crownes and Vanes of the tower was
turned over the top of the ſpindle whereon it was placed, by a very ſmall
gale of winde, and ſo both Crown and Vane hung at the foot of the ſpindle
three quarters of a year of more, at which time new ones were ſet up. The
Crown and Vane did weigh 100 weight, at leſt and was forelockt one to the top
of the ſpindle with a forelock of iron; ſurely if a greater providence then
this ſmall gale of winde had not took it off the ſpindle, it might have
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained there untill this time, but the Lord had ordered it ſo to be, that
ſome (though not all) might look upon it as <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118561:9"/>from the hand
of God, for many thouſands did ſee it and did take notice of it as from the
hand of God at that time.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. There is one thing more to be looked on as from the all
ſeeing eye of heaven, which fel out very ſtrangely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the late
King. His hand and Scepter broke off from his Statue at the Exchange, and fell
down to the ground, even at charge time, to the admiration of all the
beholders, the Change being then full of Merchants and others at the ſame
time, and the next day it was ſet up again, it was taken as a ſad Preſage
by all that beheld it; yet I believe there be many that will make no account of
theſe remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able paſſages, but will ſlight them as things not worthy
to take notice of, but my ſimple thoughts do lead me to conceive that the
falling down of the hand and Scepter, did preſage the taking of the
Government out of his hand, as is ſeen this day, and I could wiſh that all
thoſe that do ſo ſlight the former paſſages, to conſider better and
not to ſlight the next that follows, which is very remarkable.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. There was an ancient Gentlewoman which came from
<hi>Briſtoll</hi> a widdow, and had been the wife of one Mr. <hi>Cary</hi> a
Woollen Drapper on the back of <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> this woman had ſeen many
ſtrange apparitions of the late King at ſeverall times, as his Crown all
bloudy, himſelf in black, and his head off, with many other ſuch viſions
ſhe could not be quiet, untill ſhe came to <hi>London</hi> to acquaint
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with thoſe viſions which ſhe had ſeen of him, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter two
years time ſpent in ſoliciting this Noble man, and that Noble man and
others to bring her to the King, at length the Earl of <hi>Dorſet</hi> (after
much importunity) brought her to the King, where ſhe told his Majeſty all
that ſhe had ſeen of him, he gave her the hearing of it, but would give no
credit to what ſhe had ſaid, but bid take her away ſhe was a merry woman;
then when ſhe had told him all that <pb n="14" facs="tcp:118561:10"/>ſhe had ſeen of
him, ſhe returned to <hi>Briſtoll</hi> again thinking there to reſt her
ſell in peace; ſhe had not been there many dayes, but thoſe Viſions
appeared to her as at the firſt, whereupon ſhe could not contain herſelf
but muſt of force come up to <hi>London</hi> the ſecond time, to acquaint
his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty with what ſhe had ſeen of him ſince her laſt being with
him at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> but before ſhe could get to <hi>London</hi> his
Majeſty was gone to <hi>York,</hi> yet though ſhe was in years and a weakly
woman, and the journey long and tedious for ſuch a one as her ſelf to
undertake, yet ſhe muſt of neceſſity go after him to <hi>York,</hi> and
was conveyed to <hi>York</hi> in a Coach by means of a Lady, which at the
writing hereof is living neer <hi>London</hi> who can juſtifie the ſame if
any ſhould ſcruple the truth hereof, and being come to <hi>York</hi> ſhe
had admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to his preſence, where ſhe once again related to him all
that ſhe had ſeen of him ſince her laſt being with him at
<hi>Whitehall,</hi> with much praying and beſeeching him to conſider what
ſhe had ſeen and ſaid of him, but he would not harken to her, nor give
credit to what ſhe had ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, for certainly the Lord had hid
theſe things from him, and would not let him underſtand them becauſe he
would deſtroy him; for to that purpoſe the Lord did har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the heart of
<hi>Pharaob,</hi> that he ſhould not believe the wonders which
<hi>Moſes</hi> the ſervant of the Lord wrought in his fight, to make his
name known to all the world, for ſaith the Lord, <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.16. For
this cauſe have happoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thee to ſhew my power in thee, and to declare
my name in all the world; but the more plagues the Lord did ſend on
<hi>Pharaob,</hi> the more his heart was hardned by them.</p>
            <p>I could wiſh that all thoſe into whoſe hands theſe ſad
Preſages ſhall come, that they would conſider with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that
there was more then an ordinary hand in cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing this Gentlewoman being ſo
antient as ſhe was to take <pb n="15" facs="tcp:118561:10"/>upon her two ſo great
journeys as theſe were; firſt from <hi>Bristoll</hi> to <hi>London,</hi>
then to <hi>Briſtoll</hi> again, then to <hi>London,</hi> and ſo to
<hi>York,</hi> and all upon her own charge; ſurely there muſt be more then
an ordinary hand in it, which did guide this woman, ſhe being ſo ancient as
ſhe was, and no kind of diſtemper at all in her, but in a very good temper
both in mind and words, and in her behaviour very civill, as many people in
<hi>London</hi> that did talke with her concerning theſe viſions can
witneſſe.</p>
            <p n="8">☞ VIII. I have been credibly informed, that his
Highneſſe the Lord Protector that now is, being in a Gentlemans houſe at
prayer in a room wherein the Kings Picture did hang, neer about the middeſt
of prayer the Picture fell down to the ground, which was a ſad preſage to
the King, and now ſeems to be a clear teſtimony of Gods purpoſe to reject
him: but how hath the Lord Protector been preſerved in ſo many great
dangers as by Gods providence he hath gone through, in his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
ſince theſe troubles began, and that dainger which he eſcaped in the
Coach was not the leaſt, and queſtionleſſe the Lord hath appointed him
to be the man to Govern the Nation at this time, who can deny Gods
permiſſive providence.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. His Majeſty being one day at <hi>Cauſam</hi> neer
<hi>Redding</hi> playing at Cheſſe, he playing with the white men, the head
of the white King fell of, which was as ominous a preſage as any of the
reſt.</p>
            <p n="10">X. When the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> was at St.
<hi>Albons,</hi> and the generall Counſell of the Army drawing up the grand
Remonſtrance, in order to require juſtice againſt the King, the Sign of
the Kings-head beneath the hill from the Croſſe, that part of the board
between the head and ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, was broken out of the Sign, none knowing how
it came to be ſo, ſo that the head and ſhoulders were ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118561:11"/>from each other. it ſeemed then to be an ominous thing to
what did ſhortly befall him in purſuance of that Remonſtrance then
drawing up againſt him by the Army. Wherefore I would wiſh that althoſe
malignant ſpirits that are ſo bitter againſt this Government, to
conſider that there is no power given unto men upon earth but by God;
therefore let them ſit ſtill and ſee the Lords work done in truth and
righteouſineſſe, for ſurely the Lord will owne him ſo far as he doth
act for the Lord, and no underhand pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis ſhall prevail againſt him,
mauger all the Devils in hell they ſhall not touch him to do him harme, for
the Lord will be his Protector ſo long as he doth act for the Lord; but if he
act not of, and for the Lord, then the Lord will bring all his actions to
nought, and it will fall to the ground of it ſelf, as once <hi>Gamaliel</hi>
ſaid to the Jewiſh Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins, refrain from theſe men and let them alone,
for if this Counſell or this work be of men, it will come to nought, but if
it be of God you cannot overthrow it, leaſt happily ye be found fighters
againſt God, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.28, 29. And as M. <hi>Saltmarſh</hi> ſaid
once in a Sermon before the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> So long as you ſerve the
Lord, he will be with you, but if you fall from the Lord, the Lord will fall
from you. Therefore to thoſe turbulent ſpirits I will uſe our Saviour
Chriſts own words to <hi>Saul</hi> going to <hi>Damaſcus</hi> to
perſecute the people of God, It is hard for you to kick a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt prickles.
And I do now wiſh that you which are ſuch enemies againſt this
Government, to look up to God and lay aſide your own particular
intereſſe, and if there be any thing amiſſe in your hearts, caſt it
out, and leave all unto the Lord for himſelf to rectifie, for your plots and
deviſes will ſurely come to nought.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. There is one thing more yet as remarkable as the
reſt, When the King was at the high Court of Juſtice on his Tryall, the
head of his cane fell off, he ſtopping to <pb n="17" facs="tcp:118561:11"/>take it up
himſelf, took it as an ominous Preſage unto himſelf, and ſo indeed he
might have done all the former Preſages; the greateſt part of them bending
to the head; but as I ſaid before, the Lord did hide them from him. And with
my heart I wiſh that thoſe ominbus preſages, which the Lord did ſend as
forerunners of his wrath againſt him in his ſo great fall and ruin, might
deter all men of what condition ſoever to leave plotting and contriving any
further tumults or ſedicions tending to the ſhedding of any more innocent
bloud in this Nation; but let them plot what they will againſt this
Government, they will ſurely be deſtroyed in all their practiſes, as it
is evidently ſeen in the two laſt plots, for when they thought
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſecure, &amp; the childe of the Devill, as I may truly ſay,
brought to the very birth, ſee then how the Lord did fruſtrate their
actions, and with the leaſt breath of his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils brake them to pieces,
and that in a moment, as he did all the enemies of that famous Queen
<hi>Elizabeth</hi> all her life, as well before her coming to the Crown as
after. Firſt by Biſhop <hi>Bonner</hi> and his crew, by ſetting her
ſiſter Queen <hi>Mary</hi> to take away her life, and for no other cauſe,
but for profeſſing the Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt, had not the Lord
diſcovered it (in his due time) to King <hi>Philip</hi> in a warrant which
the Biſhops had ſhuffled in amongſt other warrants to be ſigned by him
for her death, but the King reading the warrant refuſed to ſign it, and
threw it aſide, but before they could bring their purpoſes to paſſe,
Queen <hi>Mary</hi> died, and then their hopes were fruſtrate, for ſhe was
preſently Crowned Queen, to the great terrour of all thoſe that did plot
her downfall, for her heart was up right unto the Lord, and the Lord kept her
from all their plots and deviſes, for after ſhe came to the Crown, what
plots, and deviſes did they not practiſe to take her life away, by
Piſtols, Poyſonings, Stabbings, and by many other helliſh 
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118561:12"/>practiſes, how many lowing buls of <hi>Baſhan</hi> did
the Pope ſend againſt her, diſcharging her Subjects of their
alſegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance unto her, animating her ſubjects to deſtroy her by any means
whatſoever, as it was plainly ſeen in the treaſons of thoſe helliſh
Conſpiratos, <hi>Lopus, Campion, Parry, Garnat, Baniſter, Summervild,
Squire,</hi> and the reſt of that Popiſh rable, and then by that never to
be forgotten deliverance of that invincible Navy, as the <hi>Spaniards</hi>
called that great Armado in 88. when they made themſelves ſure of all this
Nation, and ſo to bring it to Idolatry, for they brought with them whips of
wire, gagges, and many other inſtruments of cruelty to force this whole Land
to Popery. But bleſſed be God the ſnare is broke and we are eſcaped,
except our ſins which are innumerable do make us fall into the ſnare, for
ſurely our ſins are even ripe unto the harveſt, and there wants nothing
but the Lords putting in his ſickle to reap us, for ſurely the Lords
patience is very much in waiting for our repentance, therefore let us not defer
it any longer, leaſt the Lord caſt us off if we repent not all the
ſooner; but bleſſed and praiſed be the Lord for it, he brought that
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Armado to nought, for not one third part of them ever came home to
<hi>Spain</hi> again, and for all their malice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her, ſhe died in a
good old age full of dayes, riches and honour, for ſhe left all her coffers
full of riches and treaſure, which ſhe got from thoſe that ſought her
life, by making wars againſt them, for the Lord did proſper all her
undertakings, which ſhe took in hand, for her heart was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right unto the
Lord all her dayes (as the heart of <hi>Aſa</hi> king of <hi>Juda</hi> was)
and the Lord did keep her in ſtore to ſettle the Goſpell of Jeſus
Chriſt in this Nation and hath conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed it here almoſt 100. yeers,
praiſed be his holy name for it, and grant good Lord that it may continew in
this Nation ſo long as the Sun and Moon endureth.</p>
            <p>And now let me return unto the King in his project of 
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118561:12"/>bringing in of Popery, he had the leaſt cauſe of any in
the world to have any alliance at all with Papiſts, much leſſe to link
himſelf in the affinity of marriage with them, for look but back upon the
Powder-plot and you ſhall ſee his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, himſelf, and all their
poſterity, with all the Nobility and all the chief Gentry of this Nation,
deſigned to be blown up into the aire, (the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his
ſiſter only excepted) for they had determined to marry her to ſome
Catholick Gentleman, and ſo to have made her Queen, but God did laugh at
them, and brought them to nought, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and praiſed be his holy name
for it.</p>
            <p>But his Father and himſelf very well knew that all the
conſiderable Papiſts in <hi>England</hi> did know of it, and were ingaged
in it, and did contribute to it, and for him to make a firm league with them,
the enemies of Jeſus Chriſt was moſt abominable; but as the Lord ſaid
unto <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> Son of man turn thee, and thou ſhalt ſee greater
abominations then theſe: ſo he yet added more to all the reſt, in putting
forth that helliſh book of ſports (as his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had formerly done) which
book was put forth by the Counſell, and adviſe of the then Popiſh
Biſhops long after his coming from <hi>Spain,</hi> wherein he gives free
liberty to the people to commit all licentiouſneſſe for prophaning the
Lords day, by dancing, revelling, gaming, and all that the Devill could invent,
to the great diſhonor of God and his Sabaths, but it was contrived of ſet
purpoſe to ſilence all conſcientious Miniſters that did ſeruple the
reading of it, as many of them did) and were put from their preaching for not
reading the ſame, and alſo to draw the hearts of the rude multitude to
himſelf, if there ſhould be occaſion offered by any that ſhould
oppoſe the riſe of Popery, which the multitude is apt to do, as the
multitude of <hi>Aſia</hi> did againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> but knew no cauſe
for what they did, <pb n="20" facs="tcp:118561:13"/>the whole City being in an uproar, but
knew not for what; ſo this book was put forth to cauſe the rude multitude
to riſe in defence of the profain liberty which was given them by authority
if there ſhould be occaſion as I ſaid before, it was one of the
greateſt Mr. Pieces that ever the Devill did put on foot in this Nation (to
draw the people to himſelf) that ever was hatcht in hell, far greater then
the Powder plot, for that had deſtroyed, but the bodies of a few b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t this would have deſtroyed the
ſouls of many thouſands, if it had continued longer; It was worſe then
<hi>Balaams</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell for the <hi>Midianitiſh</hi> women to draw the
children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to commit folly and Idolatry, but he had his
reward, for he was ſlain ſhortly after by the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and
ſo will all the enemies of Jeſus Chriſt periſh in all their wicked
practiſes, if they deſiſt not in the purſuance of them.</p>
            <p>Here are pregnant examples enough to make men leave their wicked
practiſes, if they will take notice of them, which God of his mercy give all
thoſe hearts to do, that ſhall read theſe Ominous Preſages, and the
Lord give all men hearts to underſtand what it is to ſtrive againſt God.
And my hearts deſire is, that the Lord would ſtir up the hearts of thoſe
that are in authority, to put in execution that Additionall Act for the better
keeping of the Lords day, which is ſo much neglected, and the Sabbath
abuſed in the fields and Alehouſes where the people do muſter, at play as
if it were the week day, yea even in the time of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine prayer, to the great
diſhonour of God, and diſgrace to this City, and that it may be carefully
lookt into and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, he prayeth who is a lover of the Goſpell of Jeſus
Chriſt, and the peace and welfare of this Nation.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
